Sigma Kappa Sorority Records UA205
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Sigma Kappa Sorority Records
1895 -- 1956
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Sigma Kappa Sorority
UA205
1.2 Linear Feet 1 box
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series: Records; Publications; and Artifacts.
Biographical / Historical
The Omicron chapter of Sigma Kappa Sorority was founded at Jackson College in 1913. The sorority was committed to various service projects (including, as of 1956, tri-weekly volunteering at local community centers) and held social events including parties, coffees, luncheons, and bridge clubs. Lilian M. Perkins, member of the Tufts Omicron chapter, published a poetry anthology (Brave Maroon) for the national organization's sixtieth anniversary in 1936, and in 1950, also wrote and published History of Sigma Kappa 1872-1949.
During the summer of 1956, the Omicron chapter was disbanded by the national Sigma Kappa sorority for pledging two Black students, Terrie Williams Schachter and Eleanor Turpin Murrell, in spring 1956. At the time of its disbanding, Sigma Kappa had 45 members and 650 alumnae. The National Council's decision to revoke the sorority's charter was done by unanimous vote, and while no reason was officially given, a chapter at Cornell University also had its charter revoked in a similar manner after trying to pledge a Black student the same spring. The incident launched an inquiry by the Commonwealth of Massachusetts Committee on Education into the practices of Sigma Kappa National.
In October of 1956, the former members of the Omicron chapter changed the sorority's name to Thalia, which had a presence on the Tufts campus until 1960.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. It it fragile in places, and may require careful handling. Please contact DCA for further details.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the records of the Omicron chapter of Sigma Kappa Sorority, active at Tufts University from 1913 through 1956. The records mainly document the administrative functioning of the sorority chapter. Included are: meeting minutes; budgetary and other bureaucratic forms, including documents such as initiation forms, yearly dues forms, and chapter reports; correspondence with the national office and alumnae; publications, including handbooks and songbooks as well as books given to the sorority; and part of a tea set used by sorority members. The bulk of the material dates to 1933-1956. In 1956 the sorority was disbanded, likely for pledging two Black students, and the former members formed the organization Thalia in its place, an evolution documented in these records.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
This collection suffered some mold and mildew damage prior to its transfer to DCA. It underwent conservation efforts, but some materials remain discolored and may have a musty odor. Some items are fragile, and should be handled carefully.
Related Materials
Charles Trantanella Papers on Greek Life at Tufts, circa 2010 -- 2022. Tufts University Digital Collections and Archives. Medford, MA 02155.
Student life; College sorority members; Greek letter societies; Student Activities -- Student Government, Clubs, and Organizations; Sigma Kappa Sorority
- Records, 1933 -- 1956; UA205.001
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series is open for research.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records pertaining to the yearly functioning of the Sigma Kappa Omicron Chapter at Tufts University. Most records were created between 1948 and 1956. The series primarily contains meeting minutes; treasury, order/supply, life remittance, initiation, and other bureaucratic forms; and limited correspondence with alumnae and national headquarters. Most records are the result of meetings, special events, initiation, and yearly tax and budgetary events relating to the sorority. In 1956, Sigma Kappa Omicron chapter was disbanded for accepting two Black students; the former members of the Omicron chapter then decided to form Thalia in its place. The Thalia constitution is found in this series, and several of the song books show evidence of the transition from Sigma Kappa to Thalia.
  - Arrears and auditing plan, 1949 -- 1950; UA205.001.001.00001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Open for research.
  - Blank special order forms, circa 1955; UA205.001.001.00002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Blank supply order and initiation forms, 1954 -- 1956; UA205.001.001.00003 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Budgeting forms, 1948 -- 1956; UA205.001.001.00004 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chapter photograph, 1954; UA205.001.001.00005 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chapter report, officers, 1951 -- 1952; UA205.001.001.00006 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Initiation forms, 1952 -- 1956; UA205.001.001.00007 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Initiation dues, 1951 -- 1955; UA205.001.001.00008 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Life remittance membership documents and remittance forms, 1954 -- 1956; UA205.001.001.00009 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Meetings attendance, 1940 -- 1943; UA205.001.001.00010 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Meetings attendance, 1950 -- 1955; UA205.001.001.00011 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Meeting minutes, 1945 -- 1946; UA205.001.001.00012 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Meeting minutes, chapter reports, 1946 -- 1947; UA205.001.001.00013 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Meeting minutes, 1948; UA205.001.001.00014 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Meeting minutes, rosters, 1948 -- 1949; UA205.001.001.00015 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Meeting minutes, chapter reports, rosters, 1948 -- 1950; UA205.001.001.00016 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Meeting minutes, chapter reports, rosters, 1950; UA205.001.001.00017 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Meeting minutes, chapter reports, rosters, 1951; UA205.001.001.00018 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Meeting minutes, 1952; UA205.001.001.00019 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Membership, event planning, officer elections, miscellaneous, circa 1955; UA205.001.001.00020 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Monthly financial reports, 1952 -- 1956; UA205.001.001.00021 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Order forms and cash book record forms, 1956; UA205.001.001.00022 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Secretary reports, attendance, 1946 -- 1947; UA205.001.001.00023 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Sigma Kappa convention, 1952 -- 1954; UA205.001.001.00024 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Skits and songs, 1955; UA205.001.001.00025 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Tax and accounting forms, 1945 -- 1954; UA205.001.001.00026 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Treasury correspondence, 1951-- 1956; UA205.001.001.00027 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Tufts College War Memorial Gate photograph, circa 1950; UA205.001.001.00028 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Meeting minutes, 1933 -- 1938; UA205.001.002.00011 (Box 1, Volume 11)
- Publications, 1895 -- 1954; UA205.002
  This series in open for research.
  This series contains publications by the Sigma Kappa national sorority and other publications given to the Omicron chapter. Most publications date to 1895-1916. The bulk of the material consists either of handbooks and songbooks published by Sigma Kappa national from the 1940s and 1950s, or books of poetry from the early 1900s. Many of the volumes of poetry were donated to the Omicron chapter by alumna Hila Helen Small.
  - Locksley Hall and other Poems, by Alfred Lord Tennyson, 1895; UA205.002.002.00001 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - The Lady of Shalott and other Poems, by Alfred Lord Tennyson, 1895; UA205.002.002.00002 (Box 2, Volume 2)
  - The Tempest, by William Shakespeare, circa 1916; UA205.002.002.00003 (Box 2, Volume 3)
  - Travels with a Donkey and An Island Voyage, by Robert Louis Stevenson, 1909; UA205.002.002.00004 (Box 2, Volume 4)
  - The Greatest Thing in the World, by Henry Drummond, 1898; UA205.002.002.00005 (Box 2, Volume 5)
  - Kennebec, by Louise Helen Coburn, 1916; UA205.002.002.00006 (Box 2, Volume 6)
  - Songs of Sigma Kappa, by Sara L. Collins, 1907; UA205.002.002.00007 (Box 2, Volume 7)
  - Songs of Sigma Kappa, fourth edition, 1941; UA205.002.002.00008 (Box 2, Volume 8)
  - Pledge Manual, Sigma Kappa Sorority, 1950; UA205.002.002.00009 (Box 2, Volume 9)
  - Sigma Kappa Sorority Handbooks for College Chapters, 1954; UA205.002.002.00010 (Box 2, Volume 10)
- Artifacts, circa 1915 -- circa 1940; UA205.003
  This series consists of silver teaspoons and a creamer, roughly dating to 1915 and 1940 respectively. The teaspoons come from various manufacturers and are engraved with the Sigma Kappa symbol; the creamer, also engraved, was manufactured by Richfield Plate Company.
  - Engraved silver teaspoons, circa 1915; UA205.003.002.00012 (Box 2, Object 12)
  - Engraved silver creamer, circa 1940; UA205.003.002.00013 (Box 2, Object 13)